During the Super Friday Healing and Deliverance service at the SCOAN,
while Prophet T.B. Joshua was praying, a young man cried out.
Come here. What did you say?
Two of them. This is my senior brother's daughter. Her father died in 2004.
This one is our last born. They killed my mother.
Who killed your mother?
The two of them. They have confessed that they have killed my mother.
Ok. If they confessed to you, can they confess to me?
Do you have any right to say that somebody is a witch?
You have been witnessing since morning when witches themselves said that they are witches
and they will demonstrate it
and if they are not, the Spirit of God will say:,"No, they are not".
But it is not for you now to speak on their behalf.
Do not speak on their behalf saying that they are witches.
You can only say that they have problems, either sickness or disease
but for you to say that they are witches, are you a prophet?
I'm not.
How are you my brother?
They are being tortured.
Psychological torture.
Your name?
Which school are you going to?
Primary school.
Do you understand what he is saying?
Yes.
And you. Do you understand what your brother is saying?
What is he saying?
He says that I'm a witch.
He said that you are a witch?
Yes.
Are you a witch?
You are not a witch.
It's a torture.
He's afraid. You can hear the tone.
He said, " Yes".
He's not a witch.
Your brother said that you are a witch.
Yes.
Are you a witch?
Do you want to hear from me?
Yes, man of God.
I will pray for you people. These two are not witches.
I am the only person in our family that remains.
All my seniors have died.
I am the only person that can take care of them. They have rejected them.
Ok. Only you remain in the family?
Yes.
Everybody else has died?
And you are the only person that is taking care of them?
Yes. We're three at home.
Ok, then I will join your family.
Thank you, man of God.
Thank you Jesus!
Tell me, how do you want me to join?
Do you want to take me as your senior brother or your junior brother
or do you want to take me as your son?
As my father.
Ok. Jesus will be our father.
So, we will just be members of the family.
I want to see you and see what we can do to move the family forward.
Thank you, Jesus!
What are you doing for a living?
Somebody borrowed me money to sell recharge cards -
since my mother has gone.
Ok, someone borrowed you money to sell recharge cards.
Yes.
And that is what you are doing?
Have you returned the money?
No.
You have not returned the money?
Yes.
How much did the person borrow you?
He borrowed me 30,000 naira.
I borrowed some money and joined the money together and took
them from Akwa Ibom to this place.
From which state are you?
Akwa Ibom.
They are not witches.
It is the situation in the house that makes everybody a witch or a wizard.
And their situation is so grave that, if they grow big in the nearest future
and you people are not delivered today, they will call you a wizard.
Assume that you are in their position and they are in your position.
They too will call you wizard.
They are looking for where the problem is coming from
and anybody can be a scapegoat.
Who is a witch now?
Who is a wizard?
You are free. You are all children of God.
Live at peace. Thank you.
L'homme de Dieu vient de declarer que l'enfant n'est pas un sorcier -
contrairement a ce que la famille disait.
Thank you, Jesus!
Prophet T.B. Joshua prayed for the three from Akwa Ibom state
and declared that the little boy and girl accused of witchcraft were innocent
and that they are all children of God.
On Sunday, during the live service, Prophet T.B. Joshua brought their alarming case
to the attention of the congregation.
Two weeks ago, there was a brother that was called out
and claimed that the two children are witches and wizards.
After that deliverance, we began to probe into the matter.
It was a horrible issue.
Let's hear from the brother.
My name is Asuquo Etim Okon. I'm from Akwo Ibom state.
I'm 23 years old.
Last Friday, I came here to attend the prayer line
because of these two children.
They accused them.
They said that they are the ones that killed my mom.
I then took them to the Synagogue Church Of All Nations.
When we were here at the prayer line, the man of God touched my brothers.
I then shouted, "Please help me, man of God, help my brothers".
They accused them, saying that they are witches.
The man of God told me that these children are not witches.
They said that these children are the ones that killed my mom.
My mother's corpse is on the ground.
They never buried my mother's corpse.
They didn't take her to the mortuary.
They embalmed my mother and kept her body in the house.
So, these children, my father sent them away.
They rejected us and we have nowhere to go - nowhere to live.
I struggled to get money to try and do my mother's burial.
There was no money.
So, my friends started to call me.
They said that since my mother sent those ones out of the house,
they used to sleep under the transformer, in the rain.
You can look at their body now.
When you see their body, you would see that these people used to sleep under the transformer.
So, when they called me, they said that I should go back to our village
because there is something that they used to give them.
If you are really a witch, when they give you that thing, you are going to eat it and you wil die.
If you are not a witch, you will vomit it.
And if you are an enemy, when they give that thing to you, you will be able to pass through it and kill them.
So, I thought that if I do this thing for these children... . Especially this one.
Before my senior brother died, he left him in my hands
and said that as I am the only person that remains now, anywhere I go I should go with this one.
I thought of this thing and borrowed money.
When I go to town and visit my uncle, I used to watch Emmanuel TV.
I then planned and borrowed money everywhere to take them to this place.
That is why I am here.
My mother's dead body is on the ground since March
because they never burried my mom.
No one can buy a coffin to bury my mom.
I'm the only person that can take care of that.
I'm suffering. I'm jobless.
Did you listen to that? He said that his mother is late. The body is still ... where?
She's in the house. The body is not in the mortuary because there is no money
for me to take her to the mortuary.
The body is still inside the room?
Yes.
So, they cannot carry the body to the mortuary?
Since when?
Since March.
This is my brother that used to light a lantern in that house in the evening
so that rats would not eat the dead body.
He said that this is the brother that lights lantern.
Yes.
In the house?
So, that rats will not eat the dead body?
Yes.
From which state?
Akwa Ibom
So, I want those who have the heart for this situation to join me.
Those from Akwa Ibom state.
You come forward, and I will support you.
When they are going tomorrow, you can follow them to that community
and help them with whatever they need to do with the body.
If they still need more money to do the necessary and bury the woman
and restore this family back.
They are too little.
So, no matter what we give, if we do not follow them to their community
and stand by as a family to support the boy, I don't think that we have done anything at all.
So, people from Akwa Ibom, I know that they are here, and they are ready to join me
to help this family.
Our Lord Jesus Christ will lead us.
Let's hear from the little boy that used to light the lamp.
Yes, I am the one that lights the lamp. When there is no light,
the rats will eat my mother. That's why every night, I used to light the lamp.
You have heard it from the younger brother.
He said he is the one that used to light the lamp every night when there is no light
so that the rats would not eat the corpse of the mother.
You mentioned that you borrowed 30,000 naira.
Give him 300,000 naira and 30,000 naira to go and pay the debt.
Give them six bags of rice.
Thank you, man of God.
Thank you, Jesus!
Let them know that these children are not witches
because they thought that these children were the ones who killed the mother.
There's nothing like that.
Take care of the home.
Thank you.
The sum of 300,000 naira as a cash gift.
It has been handed to the brother an additional 30,000 naira which is a debt owned by him.
He said that he used the money to buy recharge cards to take care of the brothers and sisters
that were accused of witchcraft.
They had accused them of being the ones responsible for the death of their mother.
The corpse of their mother is still right in their home,
and the brother has to put on lantern every evening
to chase away the rats so that the corpse of the mother would not be eaten by rats.
The man of God has given the sum of 300,000 naira as a cash gift to them,
and also 30,000 naira for him to pay back his debt.
Man of God, God bless you!
Such a horrible case.
Due to the statement brought by the allegation of witchcraft on their family
and lack of finances, the dead body of their mother has not been buried
but was kept in a room in the family house for the past six months.
Every night one of the children would enter the dead mother's room
and light a lantern in order to prevent rats from eating the corpse of their mother.
After they had stated thieir case,
Prophet T.B. Joshua gave Asuquo and the family the sum of 300,000 naira, six bags of rice
and a Holy Bible to help take care of the family
and additional 30,000 naira to pay off the debt Asuquo owed.
Leaving The SCOAN, the Etim Okon family accompanied by the Emmanuel TV team
embarked on their journey to Akwa Ibom state on a mission to bury their late mother
whose corpse has been lying abandoned in a room for six long months
and to reconcile the feuding family, following allegations of witchcraft.
My name is Asuquo Etim Okon.
I'm from Akwa Ibom.
I'm 23 years old.
These are my brothers and sisters and our father and mother in the Lord.
The man of God (T.B. Joshua) has sent them to come with us
to our village for the burial of our mother.
My name is George Udoh.
The man of God selected us to accompany the children
to go and reconcile both families
so that we can do the burial of the mother
who died in March this year and up till now, has not been buried.
So, we thank T.B. Joshua for what he has done for Akwa Ibom state.
Knowing that their journey would break the yoke of shame and separation within the Etim Okon family,
satan tried to disrupt the mission.
Due to adverse weather conditions and bad roads, the vehicle was stuck for almost three hours.
But as Christians, we know that hard times may test us but cannot destroy us.
Because the team was carrying out an assignment from God,
no matter what constituted the obstacle on their way,
they could not be stopped.
After much effort, hard work and perseverance, the vehicle was freed
and the team continued on their journey, knowing that the road to their destination
would not be a bed of roses but God's grace was sufficient for whatever they faced.
After a long journey, they finally arrived at the family's village in Akwa Ibom state.
The very place their dead mother's corpse was laid six months earlier in March,
and where the stigma of witchcraft had been attached to the family.
The elder son leads the team by foot into the village.
Later that night, the team went to the house where the corpse was laid
This is my father's compound.
This is the room my mother's corpse is laid.
Every evening, I used to come and light the lantern here, in this house.
I light the lantern because when there is no lantern, the rats would eat
the dead body. That is why I light the lantern every night.
And that is what you have come to do now?
Yes.
Here is the son who had the cruelling task of lighting a lamp in his late mother's room every night -
in an attempt to stop rats from eating the body.
The footage you are about to watch is of a sensitive nature
and may not be suitable for all viewers, especially children.
But please take note that it is for the glory of God.
Carrying out his daily task, the boy lights the lamp.
The next day, the Emmanuel TV team return to meet the whole family, including the father.
Where are we now?
My father's house.
So this is your father's compound?
Yes.
Here we are in Akwa Ibom state with Asuquo Etim.
He said this is his father's compound.
We have come from The SCOAN - the team that the man of God sent with the evangelists -
to come for his mother's burial. He also complained to the man of God that
his mother's corpse lies in this very compound.
What is happening?
I am the owner of this house.
Mummy, we are coming from The SCOAN -
all the way from Lagos state.
These are the evangelists the man of God has sent to come with me for
my mother's burial.
I am very happy; thank you.
She said that she is very glad and happy to see us.
This is my father's compound.
This is the room where my mother's corpse lies.
My mother's dead body is inside the room.
This is where my father lives. This is my father's parlour.
For how long has your mother's dead body been in this room?
For five to six months now.
Can you tell us: How did you manage to keep your mother's dead body
for the past five to six months in this room?
Because there is no money to bury her.
So what did you do before you could keep her in this room?
Did you do anything to her body before you could keep her in this room?
For five to six months?
Yes.
What did you do? Tell us.
They embalmed her.
My brother used to light a lantern in the house.
Why?
Because of rats. If there is no lantern inside the house, rats will disturb
the dead body. They would eat the dead body.
This is where my mother's corpse is.
It is inside.
This is where I used to come and light the lantern because if there is no light,
the rats would eat my mother's body.
So, apart from you, no other person enters this room?
Nobody.
The footage you are about to watch is of a sensitive nature
and may not be suitable for all viewers, especially children.
But please take note, it is for the glory of God.
All the expenses are being paid for by Prophet T.B. Joshua.
This is my father and my step-mother - they are coming now.
Here comes the father of Asuquo - the man accused of killing his first wife
and initiating two of his children into witchcraft.
Why are all these people here?
Father, we have brought good news to your house.
Prophet T.B. Joshua sent these people from Lagos state
to follow me here because of the children that were accused of witchcraft.
They have come to let the community know that the children are not witches and wizards.
So, let them come with me and bury my late mother.
That is the reason I have brought them to come and see you.
Is this why you brought them? To come and help bury your late mother?
Thank you.
I am pleased; I am very happy.
After explaining to the father why the Emmanuel TV team had come to his house,
Asuquo proceeds to narrate their experiences at The SCOAN.
How Prophet T.B. Joshua had blessed them with the sum of 330,000 naira
and bags of rice upon hearing their ordeal.
He shows him evangelical items from the Church with Prophet T.B. Joshua's picture on them.
Let's hear what he has to say.
My name is Etim Okon Edem.
I am very glad for what my son has just said.
It makes me very happy.
They are all my children.
What I have to say concerning what the Prophet has said to my children
is that I am their father.
The witchcraft spirit they said that they are possessed with,
they said that I possessed my children with this witchcraft spirit.
I am prepared to follow my children to go to Prophet T.B. Joshua
to find out, whether I am the one who gave them the wizard spirit
or whether I have that wizard spirit.
I am very happy and at the same time these are my children.
Regarding the issue of witchcraft of which my children were accused,
I was not the one who accused my children.
I was accused of witchcraft and of being the one that possessed my children.
Now that my children have been vindicated of being witches and wizards,
I would also like to go and meet that man of God (Prophet T.B. Joshua)
so that he can also tell the whole world whether I am a wizard or not.
The late woman is my wife and these are the children she bore for me.
Five of the children are late and I'm left with five.
I am Mr Joe Edem.
I am a native of this land.
It happened exactly as Mr Etim said that he had been accused of witchcraft.
Because of that, they also accused Mr Etim of initiating his son
and this was taken to the market square.
On the action of the villagers, Mr Etim was beaten because of traditions we normally follow.
He was asked to give goats and drinks; however, there was no money.
He used his land just so that he could give these items.
Then, the next action was that the village gave an ultimatum for Mr Etim
to bury his wife and whatever concerns the burial, he would bear the full responsibility for that.
He did so.
They left the corpse of the wife with him.
They left the matter like this.
Even the child standing here, we beat him up severely in this village.
We were even about to kill him.
Because of that accusation, these children were driven out of the father's compound.
They faced a lot of hardship because when they entered someone's house,
they would pursue them out.
After some months, this one was accused of being a witch.
Then, the story became another thing entirely.
So, they were driven out.
Even the father - they called him to the village square again to fine, and so he did.
Mr Etim was accused of being the one that killed his wife
and that he joined hands with this little child standing here to kill his wife.
Because of that, they handed everything to him that he should bury his wife alone.
It was yesterday, about 5 pm that I heard the story of a team coming from Lagos
to bury this woman that is why I came to see.
Now when I came here, I saw these two.
They introduced themselves to me as members of T.B. Joshua's church.
To say it in brief, I am extremely happy and I am glad because even in this our area,
nobody would have known this. Since the man of God (Prophet T.B. Joshua) has done this for the community,
we here in this community give thanks to the Almighty God.
Mr Joe Edem, a native of Akwa Ibom state, explained how Mr Etim had been accused
of wizardry after the death of his wife and was publicly beaten and stigmatised in the society.
Two of his children were subsequently accused of witchcraft, rejected by the community
and left to their own fate.
This is the house of the chief of Mr Etim's community.
Mr Etim has brought the Emmanuel TV team here to formally introduce them to the chief.
This is the chief of the community taking his seat at the front of the house.
They explained the reason for their coming was to reconcile the family with the community
and to seek permission to bury Mr Etim's wife.
The Chief said that what Mr Etim said is true.
He was not even around when this problem started. He came and met it.
They said the man is a wizard and that he is the one that initated his
two children into that kingdom. The Chief wanted to settle the matter
but they refused 'til the whole thing scattered.
Exactly what he told you is what happened.
They even ordered, due to his stubbornness that
he should be flogged, and he was flogged.
They gave him a fine that he was supposed to pay to the village
but he did not obey. He said that he had no money.
The villagers went to his house forcefully and brought out
two she goats and slaughtered them for the villagers to eat.
They wanted to kill him.
So, now that we have come from the man of God Prophet T.B. Joshua
and the man of God has said those that were accused of being witches and wizards are innocent,
that they are not witches or wizards and that we should come with those children
to let the villagers know that they are not witches or wizards
and also to give their mother a befitting burial. What does the Chief have to say concerning this?
The Chief says he is sending his regards to the man of God
for what he has done to recondile the village and the family.
He is happy.
The Heavenly Father should give him more anointing, more grace to continue the good work of God.
We want to ask Mr Etim if he has any other thing he would like to say to the Chief
concerning the burial of his wife.
Now that the Chief has agreed that he should bury his wife, he wants to know
what the items are that they need to buy for the burial.
The Chief says that if the total amount of money is brought here,
he will buy everything, settle the villagers,
so that we can go ahead with the burial.
The total is 26,000 naira.
On behalf of the man of God, Prophet T.B. Joshua, and the Emmanuel TV team,
this is the money to buy the items that are needed for the final burial of the wife of Mr Etim Okon.
As the man of God has said that he is going to support Mr Okon's family to make sure
a befitting burial is given to his wife, this has commenced with this list that was given to us
by the Chief of this community and now we are handing over the cash to him
so that he can buy all these items
and a befitting burial can be given to the wife of Mr Okon in this community.
He says that we are free to go ahead with the burial,
that he thanks us so much and
asks that we should send his regards to the man of God, Prophet T.B. Joshua.
Having finalised the agreements concerning the burial of Mr Etim's wife,
the Emmanuel TV team present the Chief of this community
with two bags of rice as a gift from Prophet T.B. Joshua.
Thanking the Chief, the team respectfully take their leave.
Now, Mr Etim leads the Emmanuel TV team to the chief of the neighbouring community
who is also the father of his late wife.
The team comes down from the bus and approaches the house.
Mr Etim is telling his father-in-law that these people that have come with him
are the people the man of God, Prophet T.B. Joshua, sent to come
and help him bury his wife.
So, as he is here now, the father-in-law should tell him all traditional rites
so that he will observe it.
He says his name is Chief Etim Willems.
After agreeing to bury the deceased,
they discuss the items required for the burial as their tradition stands.
The Chief says that if you will comply with him and give him all that he mentioned,
you are free to go ahead with the burial.
On behalf of the man of God, Prophet T.B. Joshua,
we want to present the sum of 38,000 naira, which is the cash needed
to buy the items that were stated by the Chief for the final burial of Mr Etim Okon's wife.
So, Chief, thank you, sir.
The Chief says that as you have given him what he requested,
you can carry on with the burial.
The Chief says that it is about five months now since their daughter died
and that there was no way for them to bury her.
He thanks God for this.
The Chief says that he is very happy, and that there was no hope of this
but since the Lord has done this for him, he gives thanks to God.
The Emmanuel TV team gives the Chief 38,000 naira
to pay for the burial rites of Mr Etim's wife.
The man of God, Prophet T.B. Joshua, has sent this team to this family
to inform them that those that were accused of being witches and wizards
are not witches and wizards
and also to give a benefitting burial to their daughter who is the wife of Mr Etim Okon
who is sitting right here.
With the successful completion of the negotiation,
the Emmanuel TV team gives the Chief
the gift of two bags of rice on behalf of Prophet T.B. Joshua.
He says you should go and tell the man of God that he is happy
about what he has done for this family. He prays that the blessings of God,
should remain with him and God should extend his wisdom
so that he would continue to do that, in Jesus' name. Amen.
In order to give Mrs Aret a befitting burial,
the Emmanuel TV team made preparations to purchase a coffin.
Since the man of God has taken up the responsibility to
to give your mother a befitting burial, I think the first thing we should do now
is to get a coffin for her burial so do you have any one
that can help to go and get the coffin?
Yes, I have.
Can you call the person so that we can make preparations towards that?
We were just talking about his mother's burial
and we want someone to help us get a coffin and he has called you.
So, do you have any idea how much a coffin will cost?
The coffin is 30,000 naira. Together with the transportation, it is 36,000.
36,000 is for the coffin and the transportation?
For the coffin and the transportation.
Ok.
On behalf of the man of God, Prophet T.B. Joshua, and the Emmanuel TV team,
we are giving you the sum of 36,000 naira
as the cost for the transportation and the coffin to use in burying
the late mother of Asuquo and also the wife of Mr Etim.
Prophet T.B. Joshua has taken total responsibility for the funeral expenses.
He states that the total cost for the coffin, including transportation,
amounts to 36,000 naira,
which is promptly given to him by the Emmanuel TV team.
Later that day...
Here you can see the respectable coffin brought for the burial of Mrs Aret
whose corpse has been lying in a room for six months
due to insufficient funds for her funeral.
Here is the embalmed corpse - stiff and placed by the window -
as preparations are made to lower it into the coffin.
Following cultural traditions, they place Mrs Aret's most beautiful wears
into the coffin - her final resting place.
Just consider, if not for God's intervention, the dead body of Mrs Aret
would be left to a terrible fate.
Laying the corpse into the coffin, the family members of the deceased
continue to mourn - overcome with grief.
Closing the lid of the coffin, they prepare to move it to the church.
As the rain falls, so do the tears of the grief-stricken family members.
Here is the funeral procession as the body of Mrs Aret embarks on its final journey,
heading for the local Apostolic Church.
They finally arrive at the Apostolic Church where the funeral will take place.
This is the photograph of Mrs Aret when she was alive.
A hard-working mother of ten of whom sadly only five remain today.
The long-awaited funeral service of Mrs Aret finally begins.
I will now call on another person to take the place of
thanking God and committing this meeting to God.
We want to recognise their presence here - the team of evangelists.
We would like to stand together and greet them as a team.
Emmanuel TV and the team of evangelists, you are welcome
in Jesus' name. Let us stand up and greet them.
Emmanuel! (God With Us - Matthew 1:23)
This is our calvary greeting at The SCOAN.
We bring greetings to all of you from the man of God, Prophet T.B. Joshua in Jesus' name.
Amen.
Brethren, I have a couple of things to tell you.
Up till now, God is using people to bless other people.
As we learn from the book of Genesis, God used Joseph to bless Potiphar.
But here in the land of Abia Limi, God is using the great man of God,
Prophet T.B. Joshua, to bless the family of Etim Okon.
Are you still with me?
Yes.
The man has never been here but the Spirit of God moved him to bless
the children of this land and the people of this land. Therefore, I have a couple
of things to tell you when it is time.
Amen.
There was no written biography. I will now call on somebody from the family
to come and say something about the sister lying before us here.
Praise the Lord!
Amen.
Praise the living God!
Children of God, praise the Lord!
Amen.
This was the only junior sister that I had.
I had two sisters - a junior sister and one elder sister, which is my senior sister.
My sister suffered a lot in her marital family.
It was full of trials and temptations.
My sister had the sickness that we call "Fire burns twice".
She had another sickness that removed two of her fingers.
My sister suffered a lot because of the trials in her marital family.
She gave birth to ten children. Then, the first five died;
only the last five are alive.
Because of that, there were problems in the family.
My sister then fell sick again.
Then my brother spent a lot of money on my sister.
He took her to thirteen places for healing; there was no way.
Later on, there was no more money.
Later, my sister gave up. That day, I was at Aba city (Nigeria).
My senior sister called me. Then I didn't know what to do.
Praise the living God!
Amen.
After five or six months, my sister's dead body was still on the ground,
with no preparations for burial. Then the Almighty God, the Ancient of days,
The Lion of the tribe of Judah took the first of the living sons
to Lagos to meet with Prophet T.B. Joshua.
Then the man of God helped us today and did everything
necessary to give my sister a befitting burial.
Today, I am so glad that I don't know what to say!
I really thank my God because He is great, the Author of the Universe.
I really thank God for the burial of my sister.
I thank God for T.B. Joshua and God will reward that man abundantly.
God will give him the grace to do more than this.
Amen.
God will give him showers of blessings and open ways for the man
and the people that accompanied my sister's children all the way from Lagos
down here to my village in Akwa Ibom state.
Praise the Lord!
Amen.
Hallelujah!
What you don't even expect, God has done it today.
That is why we used to say that if God has planned a better thing for you,
and there is no way for you to get that thing,
God must cause something to happen, so that
that thing must draw faster to you and you possess your possession.
Somebody shout, 'Hallelujah'!
Hallelujah!
That is why God caused something to happen in that family
that took the son of this sister to Lagos.
Are you still with me?
This young man traced where the Prophet, the great man of God is.
He entered there and said, "God, will You open a way for me?"
God said, "I am the way, the truth and the life.
Nobody can see the Father, except by Me".
Hallelujah!
Amen.
The young man took a way to The SCOAN and
the man of God took him as his own son, not as a member of the church.
He took the responsibility of burying the mother
and also awarded the children with scholarships.
Is that not wonderful?
It is the doing of God; it is not a man's doing.
That is a great challenge to our lives.
If you want to do something for God, run fast and serve the living God.
Amen.
We will stand here and pray for T.B. Joshua
for God to open more ways for him,
equip him, protect him, and preserve his life for us.
Hallelujah!
Amen.
Prayer
After the funeral service, the people follow the coffin in procession
as the body is moved to its final resting place.
I know there is another
Fellowship in Heaven
Overcome with emotion, Asuquo, the eldest son, cries out hysterically
as his late mother is about to be laid to rest in her grave.
Here is the son who daily entered the room where his dead mother's corpse lay
to light a lamp in order to deter rats from consuming the body.
Mr Etim looks on with a solemn expression on his face
as his wife's dead body is finally laid to rest.
The coffin is lowered at long last into the grave.
A funeral song
As they begin to cover the coffin with soil,
the family, friends and well wishers bid their final farewell to Mrs Aret.
With the burial of their mother over and having successfully reconciled
with the two communities to which they belong,
they embark on a long journey back to Lagos state and The SCOAN.
Accompanied by the Emmanuel TV team,
the family once again have boarded the bus.
This time, however, they are followed by Mr Etim.
It is night time when the buses finally pull into The SCOAN's driveway.
All the children take their seats.
Among the group is also the pastor who conducted their mother's funeral,
an elder from their village and members of The SCOAN from Akwo Ibom state.
Here we can see them climbing down from the bus
after a wearing journey.
Closely followed in the next bus by Mr Etim, their father.
He has been accused of wizardry, having been labelled as the one
who initiated his two youngest children,
which was said to have caused his wife's death.
Emmanuel! God is with us!
We thank the Lord Almighty for a successful journey to and from Akwa Ibom state,
which is the state of this family - the late woman's family that has been accused
of witches and wizards before they were vindicated on Sunday
when they came to The SCOAN.
After the service, they saw the man of God in his office
and he sent delegates of the Emmanuel TV team and others to follow them
to the village for the funeral of their late mother.
Now they are back here to The SCOAN.
We want to hear from our brother here, Mr Asuquo, who is the head of the family.
Can you come forward and let us hear from you.
You are welcome, in Jesus' name.
Amen.
Can you tell us your name and where you just arrived from?
My name is Mr Asuquo Etim Okon.
We are back from Akwa Ibom.
You just arrived from Akwa Ibom state?
Yes.
Abiaje-Idibe in Orue Ottong / Oruko L.G.A. in Oron, Akwa Ibom state.
This is my father, Mr Etim Okon Edem.
This is my brother, Emmanuel Etim Okon. He is the one that used to
light a lantern over my mother's corpse.
This is my second brother, Emem Etim Okon.
This one is Lucy Etim Okon Edem.
This is my brother who was also accused of being a wizard.
His name is Etim Etim Okon.
This one is my mother's sister's son.
This is my mother's sister, Mrs Patience Edet.
This is one of the elders in our village.
This is the pastor that buried my mother.
These are the delegates from The SCOAN that followed us
to bury my mother.
How were you received in the village?
When we got there, we didn't see our father.
We went to my uncle's house and we explained to him
and he took us to the Chief's place. We explained everything to the Chief.
Later, when my father came back, we explained everything to him
and they all agreed.
We went to my mother's family and paid everything
we needed to pay for my mother's burial.
The whole village was happy; it made history in our village.
When people saw the team that the man of God sent to bury my mother,
everybody was happy. They wanted to follow us down here to Lagos
to meet with the man of God.
You mean the villagers were very happy and excited
that the man of God, Prophet T.B. Joshua, sent delegates
to go and meet all members of your family, including your father,
and also organise the funeral of your mother. Every villager was very happy?
Yes, sir.
Let us briefly hear from your dad.
Sir, can you tell us your name, age and where you come from.
My name is Mr Etim Okon Edem.
How old are you, sir?
I am 50 years old.
Can you tell us where you come from, sir.
I am from Abiage-Idibe in Orue-Offong / Oruko L.G.A.
in Oron, Akwa Ibom state.
Can our father tell us who the people are next to him.
They are my children.
I was so happy to see my children in the company of the delegates that
were sent by Prophet T.B. Joshua. I was so happy because there was no
hope for me to bury my dead wife, who was in the room where I live
the same compound. The Chief of the village was so happy.
The entire village was so happy, and they send their greetings
to the man of God.
The reason why my wife was not buried was that I had no money.
Even when I was looking for someone to buy my land in order to get money
for her burial, no one would buy the land.
We thank God Almighty that the late wife has been buried successfully
and they are here to give thanks to God for this successful burial
and successful journey from Akwa Ibom state.
We want to ask our father briefly: Is there any other reason
why he has come to The SCOAN?
The villagers accused me that I am a wizard and that I initiated
my children into the witchcraft world. I came here so that
the man of God will tell the world if I am a wizard or not.
The man said the villagers accused him of being a wizard.
They said the man initiated his own children into the witchcraft world.
As he has come, he wants the man of God to prove if he, Mr Etim, is a wizard or not.
We thank God for your life.
Can you tell us briefly what you have to say, your name, and what happened in the village.
My name is Emmanuel Etim Okon.
I come from Orue-Offong L.G.A. Aka Ibom.
The man sitting at that extreme, who is he to you?
He is my father.
Where you the one that used to light lantern
over the corpse of your mother before now?
Yes.
Before now, each time you see your mother's corpse inside the room
and you are lighting a lantern that rats would not eat the body of your mother,
how did you use to feel then?
I was not happy because there was no money to bury my mother.
Now that the man of God has sent delegates to bury your mother
and sponsored everything - buying the coffin and everything,
how do you feel?
I am very happy.
To God be the glory!
It is time now to hear from the very sister of the late woman.
Our sister, we welcome you to The SCOAN, in Jesus' name.
Amen.
Can you tell us your name and where you come from.
My name is Patience Asoqor Ayam.
Thank you very much, Ma. Can you tell us who you are to this family and to the late woman.
The late woman is my sister.
The man sitting over there is her husband.
Can you tell us what you have to say, having realised that the man of God,
Prophet T.B. Joshua, had sent delegates to go to the village
and bury your late sister. How do you feel?
I feel very happy and I am here today to testify to what happened
in the village, and I thank T.B. Joshua for sending some delegates to
Akwa Ibom state to come and bury my sister. I am very glad and happy.
Can you tell us how long your late sister's corpse was kept in the room.
It was five to six months.
Why wasn't she buried? What happened?
Her husband had no money for the burial because in our tradition,
the husband must bury the wife and do all the traditional rights.
That was the reason.
This was the reason why you people decided
to keep the corpse in the room for six months?
Yes.
You are happy that the body is buried?
I am very happy.
To God be the glory! Thank you very much.
Can we hear from the pastor who presided over the burial.
My name is Pastor J.A. Akpan. I come from Akwa Ibom state.
The night before yesterday, Prophet T.B. Joshua sent the team
for the burial arrangements to be made.
They came to me that the man of God said that I should conduct the burial.
I said, "Wow, did he know this woman before?"
They said, "No". What a great love!
He has never been there before, but the man of God took upon himself
the whole responsibility of burying the sister. I was so glad and happy
and I called my elders and told them. They were happy to join me.
The whole district joined together, and we buried the sister successfully.
That is why I am here for the first time to come and greet the man of God
and also have a spiritual talk with him.
Glory be to God. Amen.
Can we hear from one of the villagers who actually witnessed the whole incident.
I am Joe Edem.
I am a native of Abiaje-Idibe village in Orue-Offong / Oruko where
the woman died. The people here with me are from my village.
The man sitting there is Mr Etim Okon, the husband to the deceased.
The woman died about six months ago. Then, the husband was accused
that he was responsible for the death of his wife.
The whole village also accused the man that he initiated his children.
Because of this, the little money the man had all went because of
observing traditional rights. Anyone accused of being
a witch or wizard in our area, you will pay whatever you are told to pay,
otherwise, you will face the penalty.
After the man spent his money, he was financially handicapped.
There was no way he could bury his late wife.
All of a sudden, the children went out.
One fine day, I saw the young man coming with the team from
the man of God. They told me the men are from The SCOAN.
They did very well. All that we were supposed to do,
the church people helped us to do it. When I calculated
what the man of God did, I estimated it to be at least one million naira.
That is why I said I must come here to say thank you to the man of God
and to the whole church and to God Almighty for making
the burial of our wife a huge success. To God be the glory, in Jesus' name.
Amen.
After the man of God gave us 330,000 naira and six bags of rice,
he promised to send people to accompany us to the village
to bury my mother. I am so happy.
We bought a very nice casket to bury my mother. They filmed my mother.
People were very happy. I was very happy.
This thanksgiving will not finish this year. I will still continue to thank God
for what He has done in our lives because this is history in our village.
My mother has been buried.
People thought that my mother will not have a grave.
Today, my mother has a grave. I thank God for what Prophet T.B. Joshua
has done in my family. I praise God. Thank You, Jesus.
We want to listen to the family. Let them come out
and let us hear a word from them.
This is the Etim family from Akwa Ibom, Nigeria
returning to The SCOAN one week after Prophet T.B. Joshua has sent his team
to perform the burial rights for their mother.
The woman who because of false accusations of witchcraft
had remained unburied for the past six months.
Let us listen as they give thanks to God.
Emmanuel!
My name is Asuquo Etim Okon.
I am from Akwa Ibom - Abiaje-Idibe village in Orue-Offong / Oruko L.G.A.
I'm 23 years old.
Here is our father, the one that gave birth to us.
His name is Mr Etim Okon Edem.
That's my brother, Emmanuel Etim Okon -
the one that used to light a lantern in my mother's room.
This very one is my brother, Amen Etim Okon.
This one is our first daughter, Lucy Etim Okon.
These ones are the children they accused of being witches and wizards.
This one is Lucy Okon Etim, my senior brother's daughter.
This is our last born, Etim Okon Edem.
This one is my mother's sister's son.
You can see my mother's sister here.
And one man from our village has come to testify of what Prophet T.B. Joshua
has done in our village, and our pastor that gave a befittig burial to my mum.
My fathers and my sisters in the Lord, they are from Akwa Ibom.
They were sent by Prophet T.B. Joshua to escort us to Akwa Ibom state.
I want to thank God for what the man of God has done in our lives.
I was here two weeks ago because of these little ones.
They were accused in the village for being witches and wizards.
When I was here in the prayer line, I saw it as an opportunity to talk with
the man of God. I then shouted, "Man of God, help me. Help these children.
They accused them of being witches. They say that they are the ones
that killed my mother".
The man of God then said that these children are not witches.
I am happy to hear what the man of God has said.
The man of God promised to join our family.
The Sunday we were here, I told the man of God that due to this problem,
my mother's dead body is on the ground and she is not buried.
I told the man of God that there was no money to take her to the mortuary,
They embalmed her and kept her in the house.
This is my brother that used to light a lantern in the house
where my mother's dead body was kept.
When I explained everything to the man of God, the man of God then
gave us the sum of 330,000 naira and six bags of rice.
Later, the man of God promised to give these children scholarships
and he sent a team and evangelists to go with us to Akwa Ibom to bury my mum.
So, I want to stand here and thank the man of God
for what he has done in our village.
The rumours were carried everywhere about what
Prophet T.B. Joshua has done in our family.
Now, my mother is buried.
People thought that my mother would not have a grave.
Today, with the help of T.B. Joshua, my mother has a grave.
I thank God for that.
This is the money that I'm talking about.
I never spent any of this money.
When we were about to go to the burial, he also gave us extra 20 bags of rice.
People have been calling me. Even when I was inside the vehicle,
I received many calls. They said that there is no burial in our village that
would look like my mother's burial.
I thank the man of God for what he has done in our family.
Right now, we are going to listen to their father, Mr Etim Okon.
He is going to speak in their local dialect which will be translated
for us into English. Let us listen to him.
My name is Etim Okon Edem.
I am from Abiaje-Idibe village in Orue-Offong / Oruko L.G.A., Akwa Ibom state.
I was accused of being a wizard. Then, the villagers stoned and tortured me
and abandoned the corpse of my wife, saying that I should be taking
care of her until they bury her.
There was no hope of burying my wife.
The Lord took my children to The SCOAN,
where they met the man of God called Prophet T.B. Joshua.
The children explained the situation to him and what they were facing.
The man of God helped them.
In the village, I saw people I did not know before,
coming to me with my children.
They explained, "Man, rejoice, we want to bury your wife for you".
Really, I was still doubting. Then all of a sudden I said, "I agree with you people".
And they helped me. They did everything successfully.
That is why I am here.
I am also here so that the man of God will look at me and see
if I am a wizard. Thank You, Jesus.
I suffered for about 11 years because of my wife's issues. Finally she died.
And the Lord proved Himself beyond human expectations.
As I'm here, as I said earlier, I want the man of God
to look at me very well to confirm if the accusation is true or not.
That is what the man said.
Praise the Lord!
My name is Mrs Patience Asuquo Edet.
I am from Akwa Ibom state.
These are my sister's children, and this is my sister's husband.
This is the villagers' representative
and these are delegates from Lagos that Prophet T.B. Joshua sent to us.
Today, I am very happy for what God has done for me.
God has made impossibilities possible to us.
In our tradition, when a lady marries into a family,
when she dies, the husband takes responsibility for her burial.
My sister's husband doesn't even have 10 kobo to do that
because of the traditional rites surrounding the case.
But God Almighty led our son to Lagos to Prophet T.B. Joshua.
Prophet T.B. Joshua became part of our family.
He helped us by giving my sister a befitting burial.
I really thank God for Prophet T.B. Joshua
and I ask God to reward him abundantly
and the delegates he sent from Lagos to join us for my sister's burial.
Now, I am very happy.
I say Prophet T.B. Joshua, remain blessed in Jesus' name.
Praise the Lord.
I am the pastor officiating the burial of our late sister.
My name is Pastor G.E. Akpan, of the Apostolic Church.
I was transferred newly to that place.
I didn't even believe that God is still using people to bless many people.
Now, I see and know that what the Scriptures have said already
is fulfilled in the family of Mr Etim.
I did not konw that such a sister had died,
until I saw a team of evangelists from The SCOAN
sent by Prophet T.B. Joshua to pay all the rites
for the family of the deceased and for the married family too.
Later on, they came to me in the church, that such a thing had happened.
Since they mentioned the name of this prophet, I had no option
than to rise up and tell the Elders that we have a burial tomorrow morning
and none of them argued.
They told me everything, that such a sister had died. There was no hope
of burying her and now God has brought hope.
We joined hands together and gave her a befitting burial.
That is why I am here myself, to thank Prophet T.B. Joshua
for what he has done for the family of Mr Etim Okon
and the entire village of Abiaje-Idibe.
May God bless him; may God keep him.
May God extend his life for this nation and the entire world at large.
Amen.
My name is Mr Joe Edem.
I am from Abiaje-Idibe village in Orue-Offong / Oruko L.G.A., Akwa Ibom state.
I am from the same village as Mr Etim Okon.
I knew right from the beginning the problem Mr Etim was facing
because of the sickness and death of his wife.
The whole thing started as narrated.
In our tradition, when you are accused of witchcraft,
there is a certain thing you must do before entering the midst of people.
Failing to do that, you will be punished.
The whole thing bounced back on Mr Etim.
Mr Etim was accused of being a wizard, that he initiated his two children
and that he killed his wife.
And he was asked to take the responsibility as traditions demand.
Then, Mr Etim was tortured by the villagers.
Finally, they abandoned the corpse of his wife with him
to take care, while he was penniless.
The children ran away from the village. We did not know where they went.
The last time I saw them they were sleeping here and there
because nobody allowed them to enter their house in the village.
Then one day I heard the news
that the son has come with a team of men of God to bury their mother.
I went there as a villager and I witnessed everything.
I said I would come here to testify to the glory of God
what the Lord has one in my village and in the family of Mr Etim Okon.
That is why I am here.
A huge amount of money was spent on the burial.
If I am to estimate, it would be about 1 million naira.
To God be the glory in Jesus' name.
Emmanuel!
You have listened.
I know that when they mentioned 1 million naira, you were making noise.
Can 1 million buy peace?
Joy?
There's no amount of money that can buy joy.
That joy that is restored in the family.
He just mentioned 1 million. It is a small thing.
We thank God that we got to the root.
When you look at what you wil spend, you will not be able to pursue that joy.
Look at the little children.
For them to start facing this kind of trouble at this age.
Sleeping on the street.
Look at the father, the husband of the woman.
I'm just looking at him now; he's not a wizard.
He just needs to accept Jesus as his Lord and Saviour.
He's not a wizard. He's not responsible for the death.
Can you imagine. That frustration and depression is enough to kill this man
Look at him. He looks like a school boy - it's poverty, suffering.
You cannot believe that he is a father.
Look at his body. It is trouble that made him as if he wants to disappear.
Now, this trouble is removed. Give him two months and see how the body will look then.
This is to tell you what the Lord has done for them.
God has brought joy and peace to the home.
How are you, sir?
I am fine. Thank you.
I am Mr Etim Okon.
I am happy that the man of God said that I am not a wizard and that
my children are not wizards. To God be the glory in Jesus' name!
He should learn to forgive and forget the past.
Whoever accused him of being a wizard, he should forgive and forget.
Because God has forgiven him, he should also forgive everyone
and see everyone as one. He should not look back.
The pain in the past is past.
The Lord is bringing joy - wonderful joy to the home.
He should not ever begin to think or look back at those
who called him a wizard.
Having them in mind or beginning to retaliate, the punishment will be great.
Amen.
From today, I have forgiven those that accused me of being a wizard.
As God has forgiven me, I have forgiven them.
I will not think anything bad against them again.
Like I have said right from the beginning of the meeting,
our outward quality, our attitude, our behaviours -
sometimes people look at it and say, "Ah, he is a wizard. He is the cause".
I need to counsel him. He needs deliverance.
But that does not mean that he is a wizard. He is not a wizard.
He has some bad attitude towards people.
People now look at it as if he is a wizard. He is not.
Everybody has his weakness.
He has that weakness. But it does not mean he is a wizard.
And the children. Most especially the brother that used to put a lamp every night.
He is the only person that was doing this?
Yes.
You need to be delivered.
Because I'm seeing the spirit of death.
In the mighty name of Jesus Christ!
Out! In the mighty name of Jesus Christ!
Can you see the manifestation? Can you see him?
Can you see - this is coming out of him.
Can you see?
He's changing body. He's transforming.
Look at the body.
Watch your screen.
He's transforming.
You can see the movement.
Do you see?
He's transforming from one form to another.
His normal self. Because the spirit of death is over him.
He began to eat with the dead; death is around him.
If he is not delivered, they just want him to get out of the church
and when he goes out there, he will just find himself in the midst of death.
He has the spirit of death.
That is just the repercussion.
Because it was his mum, does not mean the death does not know the children.
Once they die, they die. There is nothing like relation.
Out!
Can you see?
Watch your screen.
He is getting off.
It is gone.
He cannot stand straight; there is no body.
I just want you to know what I am talking about that
he is transforming from one form to another.
That is why I carried him up.
He is transforming. His real self - it is just standing here.
He spent almost five and a half months with the dead.
For five months, he alone was the one.
He would enter there, do everything. He has become part of them.
When he is finished, the whole thing will be off. He will become a normal person.
Unlike before, when he slept, he slept with them.
In the night, even during the day, when he stands like this,
he would see people walking on their heads.
This is exactly the repercussion.
But he did it because he is a small boy. He doesn't see anything wrong with it.
If they leave him to become bigger,
the next thing is that he would turn to a witchdoctor.
And he would be seeing things.
He can begin to consult them because he has a good relationship with them.
Out, in the name of Jesus!
Out!
This man is not a wizard. But this one possessed dead spirits.
He's not a wizard. He's just naturally stubborn. He just needs to accept God.
So, the brother is free.
We have come together to support these children, let them go back to school
and whatever we can do to give to their father.
We thank God for what the Lord has achieved.
There was 300,000 naira given to the family.
Come, boy.
Because they had to go back to the village,
330,000 naira was given to the brother to pay the debt. Apart from the funeral
they have done, give them 200,000 naira making 530,000 naira
so that the children will go back to school and they should take care
of the family. The father should have a better place to stay.
I am happy for what the man of God has done for me.
I give God the glory for ever and ever. Amen.
The children should go to school.
There is a purpose for this thing to happen today.
The occasion that happened today.
It means there is a hero, God's general, among these children.
God just wants this record.
This is history. You have to be part of the history.
So, thank you.
Hallelujah.
Because it is time to celebrate.
Celebrate Jesus celebrate
Put your hands together. Come on.
Come on and celebrate.
Celebrate Jesus celebrate
He is risen
And He lives forevermore
Come on and celebrate
The resurrection of the Lord
Celebrate Jesus celebrate
He is risen
And He lives forevermore
Come on and celebrate
The resurrection of the Lord
Amen.
Thank you. Thank you very much.
TESTIMONY TIME
The father is going to speak in one of the Nigerian languages
and we have someone here who is going to translate
into English for us to understand.
So, we want him to start his testimony by telling us his name
and what God Almighty has done in his life today.
The man said he is Mr Etim Okon.
He is from a village called Abiaje-Idibe in Orue-Offong / Oruko L.G.A., Akwa Ibom state.
There was something that happened to him. His wife fell sick and she died.
Then, the family scattered because he was accused of being a wizard.
They said that he initiated his children into the witchcraft world.
Because of this, he 'saw hell' - a lot of torture and he spent all that he had.
So, there was nothing left with him to do the burial as demanded.
All of a sudden, the children left him.
One day when he was in his house, he saw his children coming with a team
sent by Prophet T.B. Joshua to his village.
They explained that they had come to give his late wife a befitting burial.
He jumped up and down and was so happy.
The burial was conducted. After that, he decided to come to
The SCOAN to see Prophet T.B. Joshua so he would
know if he was a wizard as alleged by the villagers.
That is why he is here.
This kind of thing has never happened in our area.
This is the first time of seeing someone who is not from his village, not even
from his state - giving such help to somebody.
I am very happy as the man of God looked at me and confirmed that
I am not a wizard.
I will go back joyfully to my village so thank God.
The man of God gave me 200,000 naira and a Holy Bible.
With this, I will continue to thank God for what God has done for me and
my family. To God be the glory.
I am Mr Joe Edem.
I am a native of Abiaje-Idibe village in Orue-Offong / Oruko -
the same village as Mr Etim Okon.
For some years now, he has not been together with his children because
of the problem of the sickness of his wife.
After some time, his wife died and the problem continued.
Because of this problem of being accused of being a wizard and
initiating his children into the world of witchcraft, the man 'saw hell'.
I witnessed it because I am from that place.
When there was no hope, the Lord Jesus appeared
and exactly what the other people have said happened in the life of Mr Etim.
God used Prophet T.B. Joshua of The SCOAN to
intervene in the problem they had in their family.
Now, his son can see his father as a father and talk to him but before,
it wasn't like that. Now that God has joind them together, I am very happy.
To God be the glory. In Jesus' name. Amen.
Let us listen to the pastor who officiated the burial ceremony
of Mr Etim Okon's wife.
My name is Pastor J.A. Akpan.
I am a resident pastor in Orue-Offong / Oruko, Akwa Ibom state.
I am the person officiating this burial.
I have never been here before but something led me to The SCOAN
Having seen a team of evangelists coming to me,
saying that they were sent by Prophet T.B. Joshua to pay for the burial of the
sister who died in my district, I was amazed and I asked if he knew
this woman before. They said, "No". I said, "How could this happen?"
They said, "It is the grace of God".
They paid all the rights. I called one of the elders there and asked.
He told me that since there was no hope of burying the sister quickly,
there was no need to tell me that such a thing had happened.
I thank God because God used the man of God to intervene
and do the burial. To God be the glory.
As Joshua said that as for him and his family, they will serve the Lord
we want to tell everyone of you, most especially your father,
that he should see to it he will train you all in the way of the Lord and
we pray that God Almighty will grant him the inner grace to do so, in Jesus' name.
It shall be permanent
What the Lord has done for us
Emmanuel!